让我们总结一下我们在这个特定讲座中学到的一些重要概念。
Let's summarize some of the important concepts that we've learned in this particular lecture.
在之前的讲座中，我们已经介绍了正向运动学和反向运动学的概念。
In previous lectures we've covered the concept of forward kinematics and inverse kinematics.
这是关节角度与末端执行器姿势之间的关系。在这个讲座中
This is the relationship between joint angles and the end effector pose. In this lecture
我们谈到的内容谈到了速度变换。那是两者之间的关系
what we talked about talked about the velocity transform. That's the relationship between
关节的速度和末端执行器的速度。我们已经谈过了
the velocity of the joints and the velocity of the end effector pose. We've talked about
姿势的衍生物，我们讨论了无形术语可能意味着什么。它
the derivative of the pose and we discussed intangible terms what that might mean. It
可能是末端效应器的平移速度xdot和ydot。如果机器人有三度
might be the end effector translational velocity xdot and ydot. If the robot's got three degrees
对于自由，那么末端效应器的姿势速度是xdotydot和thetadot。
of freedom, then the end effector pose velocity is xdot ydot and theta dot.
在这个讲座中，我们介绍了这个符号，希腊字母nu代表我们所说的
In this lecture, we introduced this symbol, the Greek letter nu to represent what we call
末端执行器的空间速度。这是姿势相对于时间的变化率。
the spatial velocity of the end effector. That is the rate of change of pose with respect to time.
我们已经介绍了机器人关节速度和空间速度之间的这种关系
We've introduced this relationship between the robot joint velocity and the spatial velocity
机器人的末端执行器或工具提示。这两个量与雅可比人有关
of the robot's end effector or tooltip. These two quantities are related by the Jacobian
矩阵。雅可比矩阵是由...表示的联合配置的函数
matrix. The Jacobian matrix is a function of the joint configuration represented by
向量Q.对于双连杆机器人的情况，空间速度只是xdot
the vector Q. For the case of the two-linked robot, the spatial velocity is simply xdot
和ydot和关节速度是矢量Q1dot和Q2dot。对于三连平原
and ydot and the joint velocity is the vector Q1dot and Q2dot. For the three-linked plain
操纵器，关节速度Q1dotQ2dotQ3dot和空间速度现在有一个平移
manipulator, the joint velocities Q1dot Q2dot Q3dot and the spatial velocity now has a translational
分量xdot和ydot以及旋转速度分量Qdot。所以，如果我们想到机器人
component xdot and ydot and a rotational velocity component Q dot. So if we think of the robot
末端效应器作为坐标系的一个姿势，这是一个起源的速度
end effector as a pose of a coordinate frame, this is a speed at which the origin of the
坐标框架移动和坐标框架旋转的速度。
coordinate frame moves and the speed in which the coordinate frame rotates.
雅可比矩阵有时可以是单数或接近单数。这是它的决定
The Jacobian matrix can sometimes be singular or close to singular. That is its determine
非常接近0或其条件数非常大。这就是如何做到的
very close to 0 or its condition number is very large. And this is something about how
某些笛卡尔运动会容易或尴尬。我们将通过谈话来量化这一点
easy or awkward certain Cartesian motions will be. We will quantify this a bit by talking
关于机械手的速度椭圆。我们所做的是绘制一组速度
about the velocity ellipse of the manipulator. What we did was to map a set of velocities
它位于关节速度空间中的圆上，位于笛卡尔空间的椭圆上
that lie on a circle in the joint velocity space to an ellipse on the space of the Cartesian
机器人工具的速度;在这种特殊情况下xdot和ydot。而我们可以看到
velocity of the robot tool; xdot and ydot in this particular case. And what we can see
我们有一个椭圆，表示机器人能够在这种情况下移动
is we have an ellipse which indicates that the robot is capable of moving in this case
在y方向上相当快，但在x方向上更慢。这个的形状
quite quickly in the y direction but more slowly in the x direction. The shape of this
椭圆是关节角度Q的函数。逆雅可比矩阵非常有用
ellipse is a function of the joint angles Q. The inverse Jacobian is very useful to
我们。它允许我们根据笛卡尔坐标指定刀尖的空间速度
us. It allows us to specify the spatial velocity of a tool tip in terms of Cartesian coordinates
并确定我们为实现这一目标所需的联合速度。这是非常的
and determine the joint velocities that we need in order to achieve that. This is very
在我们可能希望机器人末端执行器移动的实际应用中很有用
useful in real world applications where we might want the robot end effector to move
以确定的速度在一条直线上。
in a straight line at a determined velocity.
因此，对于双连杆机械手，我们根据笛卡尔坐标定义末端执行器速度
So for a two link manipulator, we define the end effector velocity in terms of its Cartesian
速度分量xdot和ydot并计算适当的关节角速度。和
velocity components xdot and ydot and compute the appropriate joint angle velocities. And
对于三自由度机器人，我们不仅可以指定平移
again for the three degree freedom robot, we can specify not only the translational
velocityxdot和ydot我们也可以指定坐标系的旋转速度
velocity xdot and ydot we can also specify the rotational velocity of a coordinate frame
附在机器人的尽头。这对于笛卡尔运动非常有用。还有这个
attached to the end of the robot. This is really useful for Cartesian motion. And this
技术被称为解决率运动控制。
technique is referred to as resolved rate motion control.
最后，我们讨论了如何转换相对于一个坐标定义的速度
Finally we talked about how we can translate a velocity defined with respect to one coordinate
相对于不同坐标系的帧速度。这两种速度是相关的
frame to a velocity with respect to a different coordinate frame. The two velocities are related
另一个雅可比矩阵雅可比矩阵是旋转部分的函数
by another Jacobian matrix. And that Jacobian matrix is a function of the rotational part
两个坐标系之间的相对姿势。
of the relative pose between the two coordinate frames.